{
  "reference_number": "2042",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The target must at the very least be compatible with holding warming below 2 degrees centigrade and aim to reduce net emissions\n\n of long lived GHGs below zero in the second half of the century. This will require substantial reductions in short lived GHGs. However\n given the different origins and behaviors in the atmosphere of the shorter lived gases some level of emissions is compatible with\n\n these targets. The relative treatments of different gasses in any accounting scheme will need to be carefully considered and in line\n with the latest science, i.e. more than just applying a CO2 equivalent factor to other gasses."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The target should reflect the best scientific understanding of the day and should be updated if the understanding of what is required\n to ensure a stable climate changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "The emissions budgets should reflect a scientific account of the cumulative amount of carbon New Zealand can emit without massive\n\n climate instability. This is a physical constraint and as such the budgets should not be subject to changing economic of ideological\n circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In addition to the primary consideration of climate stabilization the commission should take into account the social and economic\n\nimpacts of climate policy. In particular how energy poverty is likely to impact the economy and in particular lower income households."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Plans needs to consider a holistic picture of what a zero carbon economy would look like rather than focusing narrowly on fields like\ntransport and energy. They must also consider how the transition away from fossil fuels can be done in a just manner without unfairly\n\nimpacting the people who have less ability to adopt low carbon alternatives."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The commission should be a non partisan advisory body. Its funding should be provided independently of parliament like the judiciary."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The commission should advise on high level policy decisions. This includes ETS policy settings. However the commission should also\nadvise on the overall viability of the ETS and alternative mechanisms."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Given the wise impact of climate change and the required response, it is important that the commission include experts who can\nspeak to the wide range of affected fields. Including business, public health, infrastructure and tikanga MƒÅori."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "How we globally respond to the challenge of climate change over the next 30 years will impact every person in the world for\ncenturies. I believe that our current path is a result of tremendous shortsightedness and an abrogation of our responsibility to future\n\ngenerations and to those who are affected by climate change today. A strong Zero Carbon Bill would a be a key step towards New\nZealand doing what it needs to to ensure a hospitable planet both within my lifetime and in the future.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
